

James Wrubel

I'm an entrepreneurially-minded multidisciplinary leader with 20+ years building, launching, and scaling internet-based initiatives. I bring a strong technical perspective to business challenges (and vice versa), and I'm uniquely experienced in rallying Software Development, UX, Product Management, Data Science, DevOps, Customer Service, and Digital Marketing teams toward business objectives. I can interpret stacktraces and corporate income statements equally well, and as a leader I have a passion for creating environments that foster diversity, creativity, learning and growth.



jwrubel@gmail.com (412) 600-1036 Pittsburgh, PA USA

Work History

SVP and CTO, April 2011 - Present

THINK THROUGH LEARNING INC

Partnering with the executive team, grew TTL from \$5MM to \$20+MM in annual revenue and acquisition.

Rebuilt the company's entire product platform to support growth in usage from 150,000 students per year to 3.3 million students doing over a billion math problems per year (roughly the same size as Khan Academy).

Line manager for a 30+ member cross-functional product team including Product Management, UX, Software Engineering, Quality Assurance, DevOps, Data Science, IT, and Customer Success.

Led the company's platform expansion to mobile devices to improve the company's market reach and impact.

Championed the organization's contributions to Open Source and diversity efforts.

Revised the recruiting and hiring process for technical and product staff (documented on the development team's blog), which doubled the average tenure of engineers at Think Through Learning.

Championed the company's student data privacy and security initiative.

Technical Manager, Immersive Learning, January 2004 - March 2011

SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INSTITUTE AT CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY

Line-Of-Business Manager for the SEI CERT Program's Cyber Security e-learning support for the U.S. Department of Defense (DoD) and Federal civilian agencies. My team's mission was to invent, prototype, and launch solutions to unique problems in cyber security. Partnered with military and federal agencies to reduce risk, save money, and save lives through advanced cybersecurity training and education.

Envisioned, implemented, and championed the rollout of the Virtual Training Environment (VTE), offering on-demand hands-on training in cybersecurity, computer forensics, commercial networking products, and offensive cyber toolkits for **125,000**Cybersecurity and IT staff across the globe.

Grew the program from initial prototype to a **\$6.4m program with a staff of 18 software developers**, infrastructure engineers, and product specialists Launched first streaming video implementation on DoD backbone networks.

Concepted and implemented sandboxed training for offensive Cyber capabilities.

Solutions Architect, October 2002 - August 2003

ARNOLD WORLDWIDE

Project and technical lead focused on large-scale implementations of presentation-layer experiential and functional Web properties. Led a \$1.8 million full redesign of the corporate presence and reservation engine for a major cruise line, managing information architecture, design, copy, search engine optimization, and online video updates. Led the transfer of the Web presence of a major data warehousing company from an external hosting vendor to an internal data center.

Principal, October 2001 - August 2002

THE U PRODUCTIONS

Independent consultant to regional businesses focused on web design, development and deployment. Implement workflow-based web applications and digital marketing initiatives.

Senior Project Manager, October 2000 - October 2001

BIT GROUP, INC

Project lead for client engagements responsible for leading Web application design and development teams of up to 13. Managed schedule, budget and deliverables for a \$2m Web-based custom workflow application for the temporary staffing arm of Fidelity Investments.

Senior Project Manager, February 2000 - October 2000

ZENTROPY PARTNERS

Project manager, client partner and implementation lead for User Experience Design projects and engagements of strategic and financial importance to the organization. Acting Group Director from April 2000 through October 2000; responsibilities included resource allocation, training and development and human resources for branch project management resources.

Operations Manager, E-business Engineering, October 1997 - February 2000

GTE INTERNETWORKING, POWERED BY BBN (NOW LEVEL3)

Department controller with fiscal responsibility for internal operations and project budgets. Led the roll-out of a customizable Internet-based knowledge management product. Primary project coordinator for alpha implementations. Launched an e-business consulting and implementation group within the company connecting custom web application development with the company's core internetworking products.

Senior Application Specialist, June 1995 - October 1997

CERNER CORPORATION

Implemented Cerner's client-server clinical data repository, patient registration system and pharmacy information system at a multiple campus acute care and teaching hospital system in Ontario. Led a client team through product design and build classes, current state analysis, process improvement workshops and benefits realization seminars.

Education

The University of Michigan

BA, INDUSTRIAL PSYCHOLOGY (June 1995)
Coursework in economics, marketing, organizational behavior,
German, Eastern European culture, and leadership development.

Carnegie Mellon University

MS, IT MANAGEMENT (May 2007)

Coursework in entrepreneurism, software and SaaS pricing, software and service contracts, organizational risk management, and decision making under uncertainty.